On the 26th of August, 1768,
HMS Endeavour pulled out of the port of
Plymouth in southern England with 94
people on board.
This was the start date of the first of
James Cook's three famous voyages.
Over the next 11 years, Cook charted the
South Pacific Ocean in unprecedented
detail.
He even voyaged to Alaska and crossed
south of the Antarctic Circle.
His explorations paved the way for
Britain's colonization of Australia from
1788 onwards.
What had motivated Cook's voyages and
what new lands did he discover?
This is the story of Captain Cook, the
great explorer of the South Seas.
The man known to history as Captain
James Cook was born on the 7th of
November, 1728
in the village of Marton in Cleveland in
North Yorkshire in the north of England.
His father was also named James Cook.
Cook senior hailed from Roxburghshire in
the Scottish Borders.
After moving to Yorkshire to work as a
day laborer, he married Grace Pace in
1725.
Their first son, John, was born in
January, 1727.
James was born the following October.
They went on to have six more children.
Four of these died in infancy.
Only two sisters, Margaret and
Christiana, survived.
The family was not wealthy and were not
well connected in the way that earlier
famed English explorers like Francis
Drake and Walter Raleigh were.
The Cook family's prospects improved in
when James Cook Sr. became a farm
manager at the village of Great Ayton.
Until then, 8-year-old James had
received a rudimentary education, but
the move enabled him to attend the
fee-paying Postgate School sponsored by
his father's employer, Thomas Skottowe.
While Cook's school records no longer
survive, he is believed to have excelled
at mathematics, an important subject for
an explorer to be knowledgeable about in
the 18th century in order to calculate
lines of latitude and longitude and to
read and produce nautical maps.
The future navigator also had a keen
sense of adventure and often climbed the
local hill called Roseberry Topping.
One day, Cook decided to descend the
hill off the beaten path and was
marooned at a cliff face.
Fortunately, a ship of the British Royal
Navy was patrolling in the region after
the Jacobite pretender to the British
throne, Bonnie Prince Charlie, landed in
Scotland and threatened to march into
England.
The sentry on Roseberry Topping heard
Cook's cries for help and organized a
rescue mission.
The same year, Cook began working as a
shop assistant in the fishing port of
Staithes.
In 1747, he began a three-year
apprenticeship as a merchant seaman with
a Quaker shipowner, John Walker, in
Whitby.
Cook was a quick learner and soon
mastered the art of navigating these
coal-bearing ships south from Newcastle
to London.
After completing his apprenticeship, the
21-year-old Cook became an ordinary
seaman on the 20th of April, 1750.
By 1752, he had qualified as a mate,
testifying to his navigational skill.
At this juncture, he was a merchant navy
man.
He had not yet joined the British Royal
Navy.
In 1755,
after only 3 years as a ship's mate,
Cook received an offer from Walker to
become the master of his own ship.
It was a rapid promotion for a man who
had only been at sea for 9 years, but
Cook chose instead to enlist in the
Royal Navy.
Although the merchant navy was
considered more comfortable and more
profitable than the Royal Navy,
Cook was an ambitious young man who
recognized that the Royal Navy's culture
of meritocracy offered the prospect of
social advancement for talented naval
officers, particularly during wartime.
By the time Cook joined the Navy on the
17th of June, 1755,
and began his service aboard the 58-gun
HMS Eagle, hostilities had already
broken out between the French and
British colonists in North America.
This conflict from 1754 onwards is known
as the French and Indian Wars in North
America, and was part of a wider intense
rivalry between Britain and France
throughout the 18th century within
Europe and for colonial dominance in
North America, the Caribbean, and India.
In 1756,
the North American conflict morphed into
a wider European struggle known as the
Seven Years War that lasted down to 1763
and involved Austria, Prussia, and
Russia, too.
With the Eagle assigned to the blockade
of Brittany in northwestern France,
Cook's abilities were noticed by his
ship's captain, Hugh Palliser, who
promoted him to boatswain in January
1756.
In May, the Eagle captured a small
merchant ship from the West Indies and
Cook was ordered to bring the prize to
London.
On the 30th of May, 1757,
Cook had his first taste of naval combat
when the Eagle captured the Duc
d'Aquitaine after an hour's bombardment.
He soon qualified as ship's master with
responsibilities including navigation,
charting, and management of stores.
In the autumn of 1757, Cook received a
prestigious appointment as the master of
the 64-gun HMS Pembroke destined for
service in North America.
The war in North America had begun
poorly for the British who were defeated
on several occasions by the Marquis de
Montcalm.
By early 1758, William Pitt, the chief
strategist in the British government,
sought to leverage the superiority of
the Royal Navy by targeting French
colonial possessions in India and the
Americas while offering large subsidies
to Prussia to keep the French distracted
in Europe.
Britain's naval superiority enabled the
Royal Navy to ferry reinforcements
across the Atlantic to support a
four-pronged assault on French Canada
under the overall command of James
Abercrombie.
In February 1758, the Pembroke joined
Admiral Edward Boscawen's fleet which
arrived at Nova Scotia to support
Jeffrey Amherst and James Wolfe's
operations to capture the fortress of
Louisbourg and advance on Quebec.
Cook saw little of the six-week siege of
Louisbourg which led to the surrender of
the French garrison on the 26th of July.
The following day, he met Samuel
Holland, a Dutch military surveyor on
Wolfe's staff.
Holland was impressed by Cook's
understanding of scientific instruments
and the two swiftly became friends.
When Cook introduced Holland to his
captain, John Simcoe, the three became
inseparable.
Meanwhile, the British success at
Louisbourg was offset by Abercrombie's
defeat at Fort Ticonderoga.
As Amherst went to Boston to replace
Abercrombie as commander-in-chief,
Wolfe led a punitive campaign against
French fishing boats in the St. Lawrence
River.
The Pembroke was among the ships that
accompanied Wolfe, and while Cook had
moral reservations about the general's
conduct, he spent his time productively
charting the St. Lawrence alongside
Holland and Simcoe.
As the Pembroke wintered in Halifax,
Cook studied the charts of Newfoundland
and the Gulf of St. Lawrence, and
committed to making more accurate
topographical surveys of the coast.
In May 1759,
after Wolfe returned to North America
aboard Vice-Admiral Charles Saunders'
fleet, the Pembroke formed an advance
party that sailed up the St. Lawrence.
Cook suffered a personal tragedy when
Captain Simcoe died of pneumonia on the
15th of May, 1759.
While Cook played an important role in
helping the fleet navigate the
treacherous waters, Wolfe gave the navy
little credit for his progress up river.
On the night of the 12th of September
into the early hours of the 13th, Cook
participated in an elaborate deception
to distract the French while Wolfe's men
scaled up to the Plains of Abraham to
defeat Montcalm outside [clears throat]
Quebec in a battle that claimed the
lives of both commanders.
Cook was appointed master of the
Northumberland, the flagship of
Commodore Lord Colville, and spent a
second winter at Halifax.
For the next 2 years, Cook saw little
action, although his charts of the St.
Lawrence were praised by the Admiralty
in London and he received a bonus
payment of £50 in January 1761.
By 1762,
the French had effectively given up on
North America with the exception of the
fisheries in Newfoundland. And in
September, Colville sailed to St. John's
on the East Coast of Newfoundland to
expel a French fleet.
Cook was reunited with his old friend
Captain Palliser and he was soon
instructed to work alongside army
surveyor Joseph de Bar to survey the
fisheries of Newfoundland.
In late 1762, Cook returned to England
where the newly promoted Rear Admiral
Colville gave a positive account of his
abilities to the Admiralty.
Six weeks later, Cook married the
21-year-old Elizabeth Batts on the 21st
of December 1762.
While it remains unclear how their
relationship came about, Elizabeth and
James would have six children, five boys
and one girl.
Of the three boys who survived infancy,
two would die at sea while the third
died in his late teens.
Elizabeth would outlive all of her
children dying in 1835
aged 93.
This video is sponsored by Keyonna Beach
Antigua, the adults-only all-inclusive
boutique hotel, a hidden gem on Turner's
Beach. This superb vacation spot is a
serene retreat offering beachfront
accommodation in rustic cottages, each
with its own Bali bed on the sand.
Sanctuary cottages and plunge pool
cottages have their own private plunge
pools for total privacy and relaxation.
Two of our team members visited this
resort and stayed in a sanctuary
cottage. Their stay lived up to every
expectation they had of this little
piece of heaven on Antigua's west coast.
The private pool set amongst the vibrant
bougainvilleas is a peaceful sanctuary
and the Bali bed is a sublime haven
right by the water yet also very
private. The restaurants at Keyonna
Beach serves a la carte food without
reservations using fresh local produce,
herbs, and sustainable seafood.
This exclusively adults-only retreat has
an ethos of disconnection from the
outside world giving couples privacy,
space, and time to unwind and reconnect
with each other surrounded by the
natural beauty of Antigua.
Click the link in the description which
takes you to the Keyonna Beach website
where you'll find more information on
how to book your ideal escape at Keyonna
Beach, a true hidden treasure on the
beautiful Caribbean island of Antigua.
In spring 1763, Cook was appointed the
king's surveyor and received
instructions from Newfoundland's
governor, Thomas Graves, to survey the
island.
Cook began work on the islands of Saint
Pierre and Miquelon which were to be
handed back to France under the terms of
the Treaty of Paris signed in 1763.
He was soon rewarded with the command of
his own ship named HMS Grenville after
the new Prime Minister, George
Grenville.
Between 1763 and 1767,
Cook spent five seasons surveying
Newfoundland in the summer while
spending the winter with his family in
England.
After Palliser succeeded Graves as
governor in 1764,
Cook was instructed to survey the parts
of the island deemed most vulnerable to
the prospect of French invasion in any
future war where they might try to
reclaim Canada.
While working on the northwestern coast
in August 1764,
Cook suffered a serious accident when a
powder horn blew up in his hand.
The following July, the Grenville ran
aground and Cook was forced to unload
her cargo to refloat her.
The Admiralty recognized Cook as a
rising star and allowed him to publish
maps of Newfoundland in his own name.
On the 5th of August 1766,
Cook observed a solar eclipse and was
able to determine his exact longitude by
comparing his data with a set of
observations taken in Oxford.
Cook sent his findings to the astronomer
John Bevis and his efforts were
recognized by the Royal Society in
London.
Cook's surveys, which contributed to the
growth of the British fishing industry
in Newfoundland, ensured that his
requests for increasingly sophisticated
equipment were readily granted by the
Admiralty.
Following a successful surveying season
in 1767,
the Grenville ran aground in the Thames
Estuary, forcing Cook and his crew to go
ashore in small boats.
After spending the winter of 1767 to
1768 with his family in England, Cook
expected to return to Newfoundland to
continue his survey.
Instead, the Admiralty appointed him to
lead an expedition to the South Pacific
and commissioned him as a lieutenant on
the 25th of May.
Alongside wider political and scientific
objectives, the expedition was part of
the Royal Society's project to observe
the transit of Venus,
a rare astronomical event in which the
planet was seen moving across the face
of the Sun, offering scientists the
opportunity to calculate the distance
from the Earth to the Sun using
trigonometry.
The transit came in pairs 8 years apart,
separated by gaps of over a century.
Since the observations of the 1761
transit had been unsatisfactory,
the Royal Society planned to send
observers across the globe to record it
in a better manner in 1769.
Before Cook's appointment, the Admiralty
purchased a four-year-old collier called
the Earl of Pembroke and renamed it HMS
Endeavour.
The Endeavour would sail with just over
100 men, including several who had
sailed with Byron and Wallace on HMS
Dolphin.
These included third lieutenant John
Gore, a 38-year-old American, and
Charles Clark, the 27-year-old deputy
master's mate.
Given the Royal Society's involvement,
the Endeavour also accommodated a group
of scientists, including the young
botanist Joseph Banks, who was to
achieve great fame.
Banks brought along his Swedish friend,
Dr. Daniel Carl Solander, a compatriot
and pupil of Carl Linnaeus.
In early August, Cook received formal
instructions to sail to Tahiti to
observe the transit of Venus, alongside
secret instructions to search for the
Great Southern Continent and to chart
New Zealand and Tasmania.
Cook insisted on strict discipline, but
recognized the difficult conditions on
board and showed special concern for his
crew's welfare.
After leaving Plymouth in August 1768,
Cook called at Madeira and Tenerife
before crossing the equator on the 25th
of October and anchoring at Rio de
Janeiro on the 13th of November.
Two months and 2,000 miles later,
Endeavour approached Cape Horn, the
southern tip of South America, where
Banks and the scientists were caught up
in a snowstorm that claimed the lives of
his two African servants.
After rounding the Cape in late January
1769,
Cook made swift progress through the
South Pacific and anchored at Matavai
Bay on Tahiti on the 13th of April 1769.
The veterans of Wallis's expedition told
him about the Polynesian women who
offered their bodies in exchange for
iron, resulting in the rapid spread of
venereal disease and the removal of iron
fittings from the ship. Upon arrival,
Cook obtained permission to build a fort
and observatory named Fort Venus.
The presence of the prominent islanders
Tu Tairua and Te Pau guaranteed the
peace, while Banks proved an effective
agent in securing provisions.
However, Cook was ignorant of the social
organization on the island and angered
Tu Tairua by receiving a woman called
Purea,
who had been a powerful figure during
Wallis's visit, but had since been
reduced in status by Tu Tairua.
The Europeans also struggled to prevent
the islanders from stealing their
equipment and were unaware that the
Polynesians regarded trade as an
exchange of gifts, rather than a
commercial enterprise.
When a quadrant went missing, Cook
captured Tu Tairua and other local
chiefs and held them hostage until it
was returned.
Cook was embarrassed when Banks
retrieved the instrument after
ascertaining its whereabouts from Te Pau
and spent the following weeks making
amends.
On Saturday, the 3rd of June, 1769,
Cook observed the 6-hour transit of
Venus,
but distortion effects prevented him
from capturing its precise start and
end, and he was disappointed that his
observations contradicted those taken by
the scientists he posted elsewhere on
the island.
Cook remained at Matavai Bay for several
weeks to clean and repair the Endeavour
and take on provisions.
After 6 days surveying the island at the
end of June, Cook left Tahiti on the
11th of July.
Purea's high priest, Tupaia, hoped to
visit England and Banks persuaded Cook
to take him on board.
He proved an excellent guide for the
Endeavour as Cook visited the
neighboring islands, which he called the
Society Islands.
Cook then turned south and reached 40°
latitude, but a heavy squall convinced
him there was no land further south.
Cook approached the North Island of New
Zealand from the east and alighted at a
place he called Poverty Bay on the 8th
of October.
While Tupaia was able to communicate
with the local Maori's in his Polynesian
dialect, Cook faced a hostile reception.
During the initial encounter, a Maori
warrior was shot dead when the Europeans
attempted to come ashore.
The following day, three Maori's were
killed and three more were taken
prisoner.
Cook left Poverty Bay and made running
surveys along the east coast.
He encountered a friendlier reception at
the Bay of Plenty.
The Endeavour continued north and Cook
spent a week charting the picturesque
Bay of Islands before rounding the North
Cape in mid-December.
After struggling through heavy gales
along the west coast, Cook arrived at
Queen Charlotte Sound on the South
Island in mid-January 1770.
The crew found the local Maori's
friendly, but identified signs of
cannibalism.
After sailing through the strait between
the North and South Islands on the 1st
of February, Cook rounded the southern
cape of the North Island, which he named
Cape Palliser.
He soon completed a circuit of the
island and turned back south along the
east coast of South Island.
By early March, having reached 48°
latitude and passing Stewart Island,
which he took to be part of the
mainland, Cook concluded that there was
no land further south and made his way
up the west coast of South Island.
By late March, they had reached Cape
Farewell on the northern tip of the west
coast and they returned to Queen
Charlotte Sound.
Although Banks was [music] disappointed
to find no sign of the southern
continent, he was delighted by the 400
new plant specimens he collected across
the two islands.
Cook and his crew were ready to go home,
but the men preferred to return via the
southern Cape of Africa.
Cook took the opportunity to explore the
east coast of Australia to determine
whether Tasman's New Holland was
connected to Van Diemen's Land and also
whether New Guinea was connected to the
Australian landmass.
Stormy weather in the Tasman Sea carried
Cook too far north of Van Diemen's Land
and he sighted land which he called New
South Wales owing to the way in which
the geography reminded him of southern
Wales back in Britain.
He landed on the 28th of April in Botany
Bay.
Cook encountered hostility from the
Australian Aboriginals, people who could
not understand Tupaea's language.
As the Endeavour continued north, Cook
reached the Great Barrier Reef.
On the 11th of June, 1770,
Endeavour was grounded on a reef 20
miles from shore.
The mariners threw everything overboard
in an effort to refloat the ship and by
late afternoon, all hands were manning
the pumps as water came rushing in.
By 10:00 p.m., the crew succeeded in
refloating the Endeavour and limped to
shore for extensive repairs.
After setting sail on the 4th of August,
Cook carefully navigated the narrow
passage to clear blue water, only to
narrowly avoid running aground again on
the 16th of August.
By the end of the month, Cook sailed
through the Endeavour and Torres Straits
to prove conclusively that New Guinea
and Australia were unconnected.
While Cook was more familiar with the
Dutch East Indies, he had to negotiate
an unfriendly reception from Dutch
colonial authorities in Batavia,
modern-day Jakarta, where several of the
men succumbed to malaria, including the
Tahitian priest Tupia and his young
servant Tayata.
As Cook entered the Indian Ocean in
January 1771,
an outbreak of dysentery claimed the
lives of many others, including the
astronomer Charles Green and the artist
Sydney Parkinson.
After crossing the ocean in less than 2
months, Cook and his men spent a month
recovering at the Dutch Cape Colony,
where Cape Town is today.
The Endeavour called at Saint Helena,
Ascension Island, and the Azores before
arriving back at England on the 12th of
July 1771.
Public attention initially focused on
Banks and Solander, and King George III
ordered the plants they collected to be
taken to the Royal Gardens at Kew.
Although Cook felt sidelined by Banks,
>> [music]
>> he credited the latter's influence with
Lord Sandwich, the First Sea Lord, for
his promotion to the rank of commander
on the 2nd of August.
In mid-August, Cook was granted an
audience with King George III, who
expressed great satisfaction with his
exploits.
The Admiralty was already preparing a
second mission to search for the
Southern Continent, and in November, the
Navy acquired two colliers, which would
bear the names Resolution and Adventure.
While Cook was appointed to command
Resolution, Banks assembled a team of 15
scientists and prevailed upon Lord
Sandwich to order alterations to the
Resolution to accommodate them.
As Cook had foreseen, the resulting
changes made the ship highly unstable
and had to be removed.
When Banks then refused to join the
expedition, the Royal Society sent the
German scientist Johann Reinhold Forster
and his son Georg in his stead.
The Resolution's first lieutenant was
Richard Palliser Cooper, a kinsman of
Hugh Palliser.
Its second and third lieutenants,
Charles Clarke and Richard Pickersgill,
were veterans of the Endeavour
expedition.
The master of the Resolution was the
40-year-old Joseph Gilbert, who worked
with Cook on the Newfoundland survey.
Cook highly rated Gilbert's surveying
capabilities and delegated much of the
surveying and chart making to him.
Meanwhile, the Adventure was commanded
by Tobias Furneaux, who had been
Wallis's second lieutenant on the
Dolphin expedition to Tahiti years
earlier.
As Cook headed out to sea on the 13th of
July, 1772 to begin his second voyage,
he was impressed by the superior
qualities of his new ship.
This time, the plan was to head around
Africa and east via the Indian Ocean.
Within 3 months, the expedition reached
the Cape in Southern Africa.
Here, Cook planned his next steps in the
quest for the Southern Continent.
He had previously suggested to the
Admiralty that any such landmass would
be further south than 40° latitude. And
with Harrison's H4 chronometer at his
disposal on this voyage, he was
confident of finding the legendary
landmass.
After leaving Africa in November, Cook
spent 4 months negotiating the hazardous
oceans around Antarctica.
After reaching their first iceberg in
mid-December, Forster recorded sightings
of penguins and other previously unknown
birds.
Cook headed east and crossed the
Antarctic Circle at 66° south on the
17th of January, 1773.
Possibly becoming the first European to
officially venture into the Antarctic
region.
He lost sight of the Adventure in early
February.
After failing to find the sister ship,
Cook turned south, encountering ever
larger icebergs.
By late February, Cook reluctantly
turned north as his crew was desperate
for respite from the Antarctic gales.
He reached Dusky Sound on the South
Island of New Zealand on the 25th of
March, where he established friendly
relations with the Maoris and stayed a
month before sailing around to Queen
Charlotte Sound, the designated
rendezvous point where he and his men
were delighted to find the Adventure
anchored within.
Cook was disappointed to hear that
Furneaux had landed on Tasmania, but did
not attempt to circumnavigate the
island, and also rebuked him for poor
discipline on the Adventure.
Cook attempted to introduce agriculture
and livestock to the Maoris and learned
of the fame of Tupaia.
Apparently, the late Tahitian priest had
boasted to the Maoris during the first
voyage that he owned the Endeavour and
that the Europeans were his slaves.
In early June, the Resolution and
Adventure left New Zealand to continue
their quest. But news that the
Adventure's crew had come down with
scurvy, despite Cook's dietary
instructions to Furneaux,
forced them to find refuge in Tahiti,
threading a narrow path through the
Tuamotu Archipelago before anchoring at
Vahitahi Bay on the southeastern portion
of the island in mid-August.
Cook received a cautious welcome from
the chief, Vehiatua, whose namesake
father had recently died.
After a week, Cook headed for Matavai
Bay, where he received a more
enthusiastic reception.
After informing them of the fate of
Tupaia, Cook learned that during his
absence, the island had witnessed a
bloody civil war in which Tutaha and
Teina
had fallen in battle against the elder
Vehiatua.
The defeated high chief, Tu, survived
and retained symbolic authority.
His supporters were glad to see the
Europeans return.
The delicate situation on the island
meant that Cook struggled to
re-provision on Tahiti, but had greater
success on the nearby island of Huahine,
where he was reacquainted with the chief
Ori, whom he had befriended on his
previous expedition.
Nevertheless, Cook's stay on the island
was marred by hostilities provoked
[music] by Johann Forster, who had none
of Banks' tact in dealing with the
Polynesians.
As he had done throughout his voyages,
Cook labored in vain to limit the sexual
encounters between his men and
indigenous women.
After leaving the Society Islands, Cook
made for the Tonga Islands and
befriended a local chief named Otago on
the main island of Tongatapu, who traded
a large quantity of red feathers.
After a few days, Cook reached New
Zealand on the 21st of October,
but after putting to sea, the Resolution
and Adventure were separated again in
poor weather.
The Adventure anchored at Queen
Charlotte Sound in late November,
shortly after Cook's departure.
Cook's party had stirred up tensions
with the Maoris, who retaliated by
killing several of the adventures men.
Having covered the region south of the
Indian Ocean in the previous season,
Cook now proceeded to do the same for
the southern extremities of the Pacific.
As Cook approached Antarctica,
Resolution narrowly avoided smashing
into an iceberg on the 15th of December.
After assuring himself there could be
nothing further south, he turned
northeast.
By January 1774,
>> [music]
>> supplies were running dangerously low,
but he turned back south and reached 71°
latitude south, an extraordinary
achievement for the time.
Although Cook fell seriously ill from a
gastrointestinal issue at this time, the
Resolution nevertheless arrived safely
at Easter Island on the 14th of March to
resupply.
Cook proceeded to the Marquesas Islands,
but his illness prevented him from
appreciating their legendary beauty.
In April, Cook returned to Tahiti 7
months after his previous visit, and
quickly discovered that the islanders
were desperate to trade for the red
feathers from Tonga.
With his men in need of rest and his
ship in need of repair, he stayed for
several weeks, during which he was
dragged into a power struggle between Tu
and the chief To'ofa, and witnessed the
preparation of an invasion fleet against
the neighboring island of Moorea.
In mid-May, Cook left Tahiti for
Huahine, where he encountered opposition
after his friend Ori lost authority
among the people.
Cook left the Society Islands in early
June and reached Tonga by the end of the
month.
Owing to the cordial reception he
received on his two visits, he called
the island group the Friendly
Archipelago.
After leaving Tonga, Cook reached the
New Hebrides, present-day Vanuatu, on
the 17th of July.
He spent the next 6 weeks making a
detailed survey of the Y-shaped
archipelago.
The Europeans were slow to recognize
that the Melanesian natives here were a
different people from the Polynesians,
resulting in poor communication,
hostilities, and bloodshed.
While Cook attempted to seek
understanding with local chiefs, his
efforts were undermined by his fellow
Europeans with Forster once again the
leading culprit.
In early September, Cook arrived at the
island of New Caledonia, one of the
[music] largest in the Pacific, which he
called New Caledonia.
Since it was previously unknown to
Europeans, Cook spent the rest of the
month surveying the island, but decided
against a complete circumnavigation
owing to the treacherous shoals on the
western coast.
By the 19th of October, Cook was back at
Queen Charlotte Sound where the crew
found obvious signs of the Adventure's
visit.
Cook stayed for a month for repairs
before swiftly making for Cape Horn.
After entering the South Atlantic in
January 1775,
Cook discovered an island he called
South Georgia in honor of King George
and spent 11 days circumnavigating it.
By now, as he neared the final stretch
of the voyage, Cook had concluded that
the fabled southern continent landmass,
equivalent in size to Eurasia, did not
exist, but that there was some kind of
land around the South Pole nonetheless.
The crew was delighted when Cook turned
north, though the Resolution still had
to battle the elements on its way to the
Cape, where Cook was angered by the news
that the Adventure had returned to
England in July 1774.
After 5 weeks at the Cape, the
Resolution headed home and reached
Portsmouth on the 30th of July, 1775.
In contrast to the death toll on his
first voyage, Cook lost only four men in
his second expedition.
His success earned him further promotion
and another audience with King George.
Cook also received a sinecure at the
Royal Naval Hospital in Greenwich, where
he prepared his journals for
publication, while he was also elected
as a fellow of the Royal Society in
March, 1776.
He was, nevertheless, keen to return to
sea.
A third voyage followed almost
immediately.
Cook's primary mission in his final
voyage was to search for the Northwest
Passage, the route over Canada and
Alaska between the Atlantic and Pacific
Oceans, which English mariners had been
searching for unsuccessfully since the
16th century.
Cook continued to command the
Resolution, but was unaware that it was
poorly refitted owing to corruption at
the Deptford Dockyard.
He welcomed back John Gore as his first
lieutenant, while his second lieutenant,
James King, was a gifted intellectual
recommended by Palliser.
The Resolution's master, William Bligh,
would later achieve notoriety as the
captain of HMS Bounty, on which the
famous mutiny occurred.
Meanwhile, Charles Clerke was to command
HMS Discovery, the second ship on the
expedition.
Owing to his troubles with Banks and
Forster, Cook refused to take any
professional scientists, and the caliber
of his crew was also much lower.
The 48-year-old Cook was also in poorer
physical and mental health than during
his previous expeditions.
In June, 1776,
he bid farewell to his wife Elizabeth
for the last time.
After leaving Plymouth on the 12th of
July, he discovered that the ship was
leaking.
Nevertheless, Cook pushed on and arrived
at the Cape in October for repairs.
The Discovery arrived 3 weeks later and
also put in for serious repairs.
After passing the Prince Edward Islands
at Christmas, Cook reached the Kerguelen
Archipelago,
a chain of islands in the South Sea
between Southern Africa and Australia,
named after the French navigator who had
found them in 1772.
Having replenished the ship's larder
with the fauna on Grande Terre, the main
island,
Cook surveyed the island before leaving
for New Zealand.
After a brief stop in Tasmania in late
January 1777,
Cook continued to Queen Charlotte Sound.
While the men who had previously sailed
on the Adventure expected Cook to avenge
their shipmates lost on the earlier
voyage, Cook assured the Maoris that he
had come in peace.
Cook's entourage included Omai, a young
Polynesian who had joined the Adventure
from the island of Raiatea, and was now
heading home after achieving celebrity
status in England.
As tensions simmered below the surface,
the Maoris were astonished by the
horses, cattle, sheep, and goats that
Cook had brought from England and the
Cape with the intention of introducing
them to New Zealand.
As the men of the Discovery complained
that Cook was treating the Maoris better
than Englishmen, Cook left New Zealand
and made slow progress towards the
Society Islands.
In May, he stopped for supplies at the
Tongan island of Nomuka, where he
entertained Finau, the chief of the
island of Vava'u, on board the
Resolution.
Finau then persuaded the Europeans to
anchor at the island of Lifuka, where he
and the local chiefs presented Cook and
Omai with a large supply of food.
However, relations deteriorated when
Clark punished the son of a Tongan chief
for attempting to steal a cat from the
Discovery.
Finau then secretly conspired with the
islanders to attack the Europeans, but
they lost courage and took no action.
As Finau subtly encouraged Cook to
depart, the high chief, Poulaho,
befriended Cook and led the two ships to
Tongatapu.
The Europeans remained on the island for
a month, and the initial goodwill
gradually dissipated as the Tongans
continued to steal from the Europeans,
and Cook mercilessly flogged his men for
their disproportionate response.
Shortly before his departure on the 17th
of July, Poulaho invited Cook to
participate in a religious ceremony,
during which the latter unwittingly
broke several local customs.
The word taboo would subsequently enter
into the English language as a way of
describing the violation of social norms
following this event.
The term is derived from the Polynesian
word tapu to describe sacred
prohibitions.
Although Cook heard about the islands of
Fiji and Samoa from the Tongans, he made
straight for Tahiti.
He arrived at Vaiete piha bay in
mid-August and learned that the young
Vehiatua had died and was succeeded by a
13-year-old brother of the same name.
10 days later, Cook led his men to
Matavai Bay, where he entertained Tu and
his family on board the Resolution.
Cook hoped to leave Omai with two, but
the young man insulted the chief's
family by refusing to marry Tu's younger
sister because he did not find her
attractive.
Meanwhile, Tahiti had been at war with
Moorea with little success, and To'ofa
asked Cook to join a renewed assault.
Cook declined, but was granted
permission to observe a religious
ceremony that involved human sacrifice
and subsequently registered his disgust
with To'ofa.
Meanwhile, Tu's reluctance to back up
To'ofa provoked resentment against the
former, forcing Cook to come to Tu's
defense.
After Tu made peace with Moorea, Cook
left a supply of livestock for the
Tahitians and visited Moorea
following a dispute with its chief over
a stolen goat. Cook launched a punitive
expedition.
All of this was deeply unsatisfactory.
On his third voyage, Cook was basically
being pulled into local squabbles across
Polynesia and achieving little while
also struggling to maintain discipline
amongst his own men.
In December 1777,
10 months behind schedule, Cook finally
sailed north to seek the Northwest
Passage.
On Christmas Eve, Cook sighted the large
inhabited island of Kiritimati, which he
called Christmas Island.
In January 1778, he made his discovery
of the Hawaiian Islands, the inhabitants
of which were related to the
Polynesians.
Cook did not linger for long and resumed
his northern course to latitude 45
before heading east.
He appeared off the coast of present-day
Oregon on the 7th of March 1778.
Interestingly, on the other side of the
continent, the Patriots were at war with
the British Crown to establish the
United States.
By the end of the month, Cook arrived at
Nootka Sound on Vancouver Island, later
named after the naval officer George
Vancouver, who was then a midshipman on
the Discovery, but who led a famous
voyage to the Pacific Northwest in the
early 1790s.
While repairing their ships, the men
eagerly exchanged iron and brass for
prized furs.
The shoddy work of the Deptford dockyard
struggled to hold up as Cook sailed
north into the Gulf of Alaska in May.
He struggled to make sense of the
accounts of Gerhard von Müller and Jacob
von Stählin, a pair of German scholars
who had written about Vitus Bering's
voyages in the northern Pacific back in
the 1720s and 1730s.
As he followed the Alaska coast, Cook
scouted several inlets, including one
that would later bear his name.
The spot he anchored the Resolution in
was named Anchor Point, and later became
the site of the city of Anchorage.
Cook spent 10 days exploring the two
rivers that branched out from the inlet,
but failed to conclusively prove it was
a dead end.
By late June, Cook reached the
Aleutians, a vast chain of islands
extending from Alaska towards Russia.
He gathered intelligence about the
Russian presence here from the local
Inuit people.
Then, in August, Cook finally sailed
through the Bering Strait and reached a
latitude of 70° north, where he
encountered thick ice that prevented him
from achieving his ambitions of sailing
home via the long-sought-after Northwest
Passage.
He consoled himself by making surveys of
the Siberian and Alaskan coastlines.
Cook then befriended a group of Russian
fur traders on the island of Unalaska
who invited him to spend the winter at
Petropavlovsk [music]
in Kamchatka, but he opted instead to
sail south towards a fatal rendezvous in
Hawaii.
On the 17th of January 1779,
Cook's expedition landed at Kealakekua
Bay in the Hawaiian Islands.
Having heard the tale of Cook's arrival
at Kauai almost exactly a year earlier,
the Hawaiians honored him as Lono, a
local deity of fertility and
agriculture.
However, on this second visit, some of
Cook's crew began abusing the natives'
hospitality.
In early February, the chief,
Kalani'ōpu'u, urged Cook to set sail
hoping to be rid of the Europeans.
The navigator did so, but he was forced
to return to Kealakekua Bay when his
mast was damaged in a storm.
Kalani'ōpu'u,
whose people used [music] very different
kinds of ships, struggled to understand
why Cook had returned and feared that he
now meant to stay and try to rule over
his people.
Tensions escalated and on the 14th of
February 1779,
Cook attempted to abduct the chief to
gain leverage over the Hawaiians.
In the ensuing clash, the islanders
fought back and killed Cook and several
of his crew.
Cook's body was then dismembered and
parts of it were distributed amongst the
Hawaiian chiefs.
Although this struck Cook's fellow
mariners as an act of savagery,
it was actually a sign of respect for an
esteemed slain adversary amongst the
natives.
Cook's demise highlights the tensions
between scientific discovery and
colonialism in the European voyages of
exploration.
After his death at the hands of the
Hawaiians, at the age of 50,
Cook's remains were eventually recovered
by his deputy, Charles Clark, who gave
them a dignified burial at sea.
Cook's explorations came to a violent
end in 1779,
but his voyages of exploration and the
discoveries he made impacted on world
history down to the present day.
His legacy is easily found on the world
map, with the Cook Strait separating the
North and South Islands of New Zealand,
the Cook Islands in Polynesia, and the
Cook Inlet in Alaska, all named after
him.
As a young man, James Cook can hardly
have imagined that he would embark on
anything like his three voyages of
discovery between 1768 and 1779.
He hailed from a very humble family in
northern England, and the Cooks had no
real connections to the sea.
However, this was an era in which
Britain was rapidly emerging onto the
world stage as the globe's greatest
naval and trading power. A life at sea
was a good potential career for many
English teenagers from modest
backgrounds like Cook, and it is the one
he chose to pursue.
His talent as a mariner enabled him to
rise from obscurity in the 1750s.
During the Seven Years' War, he was
instrumental in Britain's victory over
the French in Canada, and he came to the
attention of the Royal Navy as a skilled
surveyor.
During his first two voyages, he
circumnavigated New Zealand, charted the
East Coast of Australia,
disproved the notion of a great southern
continent, and put Vanuatu and New
Caledonia on the map.
Despite the problems associated with his
third and final voyage, he put Hawaii on
the map in the minds of Europeans,
encouraging renewed interest in the
Pacific from France, Spain, and Russia.
He even voyaged as far north as the
Bering Straits and charted the coasts of
Alaska and Kamchatka.
Cook was also a key figure in the early
exploration of the Antarctic Circle.
Yet, while Cook's expeditions expanded
European knowledge of the world in a way
which was only rivaled by the voyages of
Christopher Columbus and Ferdinand
Magellan between the 1490s and 1520s,
they were not without controversy.
Notably, his interactions with the
Polynesians and other indigenous
peoples.
Although Cook himself was reluctant to
use lethal force until his last voyage,
his men showed less restraint.
Ultimately, his voyages opened up a
century-long period in which Britain and
France began colonizing Australia, New
Zealand, and the many island chains of
the South Pacific.
What do you think of Captain Cook?
Was he a great explorer who made a major
contribution to our understanding of the
world? Or did he open the door to the
exploitation and colonization of
Australia, New Zealand, and the many
islands of the South Pacific Ocean?
Please, let us know in the comments
section and in the meantime, thank you
very much for watching.
>> Mhm.